software engineering radio episode 69 so
are part 5 with Nicholas Otis
[Music]
welcome this nurse to another episode of
se radio at this time and interview with
Nikko your cities on as a way but before
we actually get into the meat of the
topic I really have to come back to the
listener survey currently we have about
10% of the downloads in survey
participation so 90% of the people who
download this podcast don't fill in the
survey now why is that
to be honest I'm a little bit frustrated
here I mean you know it's not too much
to expect that as a kind of thank you to
the podcast you just go and and fill in
the listener survey so um I don't know
maybe people don't don't actually listen
they just download and don't hear me ask
them to to please fill in the podcast or
maybe that just don't care so um well
well it doesn't help to motivate to do
this thing so please consider to go back
to our website click on the survey link
and actually give us some feedback about
what you think about the podcast about
what you want to hear and help us tailor
the podcast better and and and also get
an understanding of who our audience are
what the structure of the audience is
well let's go back to the actual topic
today this one will be a little bit a
different episode because we are not
going to look at technical aspects of as
a way but rather on some you know how
SOA influences processes the culture in
began the price and stuff and in order
to do this we have a guest
Nikolaj suta's some of you might know
him from his C++ days and if he you know
maybe we're going to talk about C++ C++
but his new topic is SOA
so Nico why don't you introduce yourself
a little bit and yes hello everybody
introducing well I come from a technical
perspective of software development and
my major focus has been for years now
large systems so I got involved for
example in one big project at a mobile
phone company and international mobile
phone company working for the CRM
department that is
simulation staff and their company
decided to work with SOA in fact - yeah
in introduce SOA in their company and
while we complained so much about what
was already there that I got the job to
be a team lead for the real realization
of SOA in that company so I was the real
realization well it's it's different
from theory and it's different from
ivory tower so you said there is some
cops out some enterprise strategy which
doesn't really work and you were in
charge of doing the pragmatics or or no
no it's it's well yes I know one problem
was that the main focus was on technical
details and SOA is not a technical issue
it is it has some technical aspects but
SOA is a business strategy for major
companies and you have to deal with
processes you have to deal with
architecture you have to deal with
organizations and/or charts okay so
you're saying all this discussion about
interaction styles orchestration loosely
coupling stuff messaging eai a web
services it's not yet really the point
this might be interesting at some at
some stage but the more important aspect
is is changing the culture of the
organization or the way it works
organizationally it doesn't work usually
without changing the organization or
having an appropriate organization which
might already be there and but of course
to discuss with your CEOs and CTOs
you talk about for example loose
coupling mmm so for example loose
coupling explains why you why you say I
need load balancing fail
/ mechanisms etc and but this leads as a
consequence to having not a common
business object model and and this has
some big impacts for organizations
because suddenly different teams have to
map data and this influences resources
this influences the way you develop
software so this is this is still a
pretty technical aspect for example a
very important aspect is that the whole
idea of SOA is distributed computing
with different ownership and the
important aspect of the different
different ownership that's that's what
qualifies SOA as an appropriate solution
so different ownership of data or
services or of yeah you can say of data
of responsibilities and so whether you
have different departments whether you
have different companies involved
doesn't matter the important point is
that you
from an organizational point of view
have no control about everything so you
have to collaborate from the beginning
and there are different bachelors there
are different schedules involved so you
need this has an high influence on
processes ok so let's look at some of
these topics specifically so one thing I
heard you talk about earlier is the idea
of not having this the centralized large
business object model so maybe let you
should briefly explain what this is and
why doesn't work in as a way environment
one thing you learn with real large
systems is you can't use bottlenecks
yeah and that is you have to decouple
things in a way that you can implement
one aspect of the system without
influencing other aspects of the system
decoupling or looser coupling is is a
general concept behind that they have
been a lot of trials to
to solve your business in a way that you
say let's harmonize things let's get a
common understanding of what an address
is what a customer is what the contract
is etc and it turns out that just from
an organizational point of view you
can't harmonize the concept of a
customer there are too many different
views if you try that either you never
succeed
oh you succeed in a way that it doesn't
fit for all back ends if theoretically
in large systems you even don't have
that problem then the final problem
arise that is if one system changes the
shared idea of what is a customer and
the other systems use this concept
technically use it as in the same way
then the other systems have to make
corresponding changes and that that's
not possible and not one organizational
like department decides to change
something that would require that the
other adapt their stuff basically at the
same time and that you say that's not
realistic yes well you might you might
have some some migration strategy but
it's it's still too expensive that to
say all people have to react on all
business aspects of a customer in the
whole enterprise and therefore deal with
the fact that you have different views
of customers in your enterprise in your
project and you know the interesting
thing or example I have is the most my
major customer is it's a mobile phone
company and as part of a general
telephone company international
telephone company and the most
complicated data type
we share in this SOA infrastructure
among all the systems is the data type
of a phone number
containing a country code area code and
then local number trying for example to
harmonize an address type was not
possible similarly they couldn't come to
a common conclusion this does not mean
that we don't have a general common idea
of what address is we have we have
general services to change an address
but they map to different address data
in different backends
so the solution is then having letting
every organizational unit every service
have its own data structure and only the
client has to know this and and if the
client uses several of these services
with different data structures the
client program has to somehow translate
yeah except that things are
heterogeneous that means you have
different data different platforms
different middleware and deal with what
comes from this point often people ask
me is SOA something new something
evolutionary yeah and and I think for me
this is some kind of revolutionary
aspect of SOA there is like an eighth
loyalty where but we change everything
by accepting that requirements change in
SOA we accept that we don't have
homogeneous system but isn't that
somehow the opposite of what's may be
commonly thought because as you said
before SOA is often introduced into an
organization in order to harmonize this
and that services there should be
reusable ideally you want to harmonize
the middleware so and you're saying
that's all basically not going to work
for the reasons we just discussed so
you'll have different middlewares you
have different notions or definitions of
what a customer or telephone number is
so I mean I I see what you're saying I
think I probably agree but but it's
isn't that a little bit different to
common belief from from my perspective
then the main reason to introduce SOA is
getting flexible based on the fact that
you have distributed business processes
and responsibilities and that might help
to get better reusability
but reusability should not be your major
business case for SOA because it takes a
long time that it happens with however
sometimes you sell it that way
because it seemed the tricky thing with
large systems is that you if you are the
argument with logic that works for small
system that's that's box when you have
control about everything then people
assume that this is intuitive if they
say yes it's that way and it sounds so
familiar so just saying let's introduce
a customer service and then the a
service set returns the data of a
customer and then saying and you can
reuse this service in any application
then it's this sounds very reasonable in
fact in practice we have about 20
different services that return customer
data part of this the the reasons for
differences is that different data is
used and that performance is an issue we
talked about that in this and one of the
previous episodes of the SOA discussion
and se radio but but go on
I just wanted to connect okay yeah and
what I learned in the past is that if
you introduced SOA and in really a large
enterprise not less a prototype with 10
services or so here if you really have
something like 30 systems combined with
different middleware and hundreds of
services which I see very very very
rarely in practice really in production
mode then use a factor of 1 is a proof
for good work that means use it for yeah
that means that
if an average every service is used by
one consumer then you have done a good
work but if the average is one that you
can't ever have set more on the more
than one consumer because you can't have
half a consumer using it right oh yes
you have have we have it's of course if
you design large distributed processes
you design things yet that turn out to
be different and in practice it means
there are services deployed that are not
in use okay so in theory you have yes so
in practice you have when you have
hundreds of service and you have a user
factor of one you have made a good job
and experiences show that that in
companies that run SOA for three or four
years you come to a user factor of three
or four with it which is usually a sign
of an excellent job and so don't don't
make your expectations too high on this
business case this is part of the reason
but this is not your primary winning
strategy here I'd like to look at or add
a little like historic view you've been
doing large systems for a while and I
know that we've been on a common project
a while ago in Hanover and and that was
also a large banking system it was not
as a way because the term wasn't
invented yet so I would like to hear
what what do you think compared to what
you did back then and it's probably
progress called a component based
architecture I guess how is what you
start what you do at this telecom thing
how is it different I mean is it the
same thing so what are the real
differences between four years ago
component based development and two
thousand six or seven as a way is it is
it the same thing or what has changed
actually well are the challenges the
real challenges are made are they the
same technically it is pretty similar
you know in fact
when I kid when I had to draw slides
about the general architecture of the
SOA system now in the mobile phone
company I could reuse slides from that
project from the banking project because
we had back we had different backends we
had we had some middleware we had to
wrap backends in a way said that we as
abstract business tasks and we have some
front-end so the only difference was
that that I had two replies solid lines
by pipes because a pipe is a symbol for
the Enterprise Service bus and and it
looked that way that due to the pipe
concept every service or every system
component code talked with any other
system component so immediately we got
the question of security so if you have
your basic services that changed the
address of a specific back-end of course
you don't want that that the front ends
call these services directly because and
then each front and has to call and make
sure that that all these services are
called so you introduce some composed
services that change the address and
yeah you want to make sure that that
front ends use that so I said not the
banking services so you mentioned
Enterprise Service bus what's that
I mean do you have something like that
at this telecom company well Enterprise
Service bus is is a concept it's not a
tool you can have a service bus without
having any specific process or hardware
running it's it's just I think it's it's
another word for the infrastructure of
SOA right so it's more or less a
messaging system yeah so I mean I mean
services are messages you send around so
yeah
part of it is some messaging system but
the tech can be a lot more task and for
example intelligent routing of messages
would be a task monitoring is a task on
maybe managing business activity
monitoring versus learn how your
services flow
at runtime through your system and then
make business decisions bait based on
this monitoring this concept is a
concept I have not seen in reality yet
but but this is part of the idea which
usually is but less usually sold to the
managers ok another thing that I think
is quite interesting is this versioning
aspect I mean if you have one service
changing its data structure and the
other client or whatever using it and
and you don't want to impose that the
client changes as you change the service
definition how do you do this I mean you
have to be able to be tolerant to change
this version stuff yeah it is there the
interesting thing was with with a major
concept of SOA a namely loose coupling
is that you have to decide your amount
of loose coupling because loose coupling
has some benefits introduced some
benefits but usually loose coupling
leads to drawbacks for example if you
use a synchronous sync messaging if you
don't get the answer immediately your
the systems you exchange messages with
has not to be online but you get your
answer later and have to deal with it
yeah so coming back to your question the
question is are we loose coupled in a
way that automatically clients use the
latest available version of some service
a provider provides which is often told
in theory that this is a good idea our
experience is that in practice this is a
pretty bad idea if you want to have very
stable systems running and and key in
our mobile phone company is that the
services one when when it whenever
customer calls in to get some support
there on services that send customer
data
to the call center agent so this service
must run when we introduce some updates
for example we have a new attribute
customers have and we say ok this is a
new this is a new attribute even it
might be backward compatible or at least
from from non-functional aspects
backward compatible then we introduce
the data that we make mistakes and that
that isn't in fact compatible but you
just take all that let me just well
introduce a new back ok ok ok so and
this happens in practice of course and
so so as a general rule we say whenever
a service is in production mode it is
fixed hmm so references to it are fixed
and don't automatically switch to newer
versions right you have to switch
explicitly to a new version of this
service which of course implies that we
have a lot of versions of services yeah
when you get never get rid of the old
crap we get we we get but this is a
something you have to deal with from a
from a service lifecycle and as always
in in large companies withdrawing
existing code without getting some
functional benefit for your business
it's an investment in it's hard to how
to realize because well you pay money
for maintainability and usually your
short earnings are more important yes
it's a garbage collection problem right
you have to find out that actually
nobody is using it anymore in order to
be able to read no throw it that's
that's not the problem because in in
almost every real running SOA you know
who is calling the service so it's not
like you have these services which are
provided by somebody and which are like
publicly available in some kind of
repository and then there is somebody
using it you do know your client yeah I
I don't think anything works without
that idea it was that without that
concept so do you have maybe maybe there
might be a public marketplace
whether it was about in an enterprise
you have to know your dependencies
because you have to know who who has to
get informed when you change something
when you when there are problems etc so
so so do you have some kind of registry
then that is used at runtime to discover
stuff well it's it's part of the
Enterprise Service bus
Morning Glory mmm of course you need the
data but how you realize that in
practice depends you might have a
registry you might well its provider
might write a log file with with seeing
who is calling so that that's enough
that's enough to get an understanding to
know I can withdraw the service or I
have to write some consumers and message
about well couldn't you please switch to
the new version every in the end I think
it depends on whether the amount of
services you have is still small enough
to be managed manually I I suspect I
mean I haven't seen that either but if
the number of service really gets big
it's probably not as easy anymore you
know people manually looking through the
log files or something so you need
infrastructure that that manages the
service lifecycle and then automatically
deploys and unn deploys and withdraws
things maybe I'm not saying this is
something you should do in the beginning
or that's even something anybody ever
did but might be no I I don't think
you're you're right
ok the concept of SOA is the central ISM
that means you you have somebody
responsible for some functionality and
that let's say Department or back-end
provide some services and from their
point of view they are pretty small they
can manage that you don't need central
control over there because somebody is
responsible for this service and they
would usually not have a size that that
they are not well that they can't manage
there are their responsibilities and
their interfaces anymore so you don't
need a view of all services to do to
deal with service life cycles
you only need
this this general view of all services
if you either have the idea of that it
works plug and play yeah which doesn't
work in practice really and and the
other idea but
you'd leave this the place if you don't
have clear responsibilities of
functionality in your enterprise and you
need some customer data it helps to see
well here are some services and this
service looks like it is what I need but
this is only to find the right person to
talk to so that's an organizational
problem and then you yeah yes I I don't
I don't think well that from a technical
point you might need for loose coupling
registries but from an from an
organization point of view the idea of
SOA is introducing D centralism and that
does not necessarily mean that you
introduced centralized repository so I
think you should be very careful with
that okay so before we take a look at
business processes in that context let's
have a brief look at your experience
with current technology and we're
recording this by the way the beginning
of 2007 who knows when it's going to be
broadcasted and we're just to continue
that we'd really like to thank the six
datacom people too because they gave us
this room at the opie conference of
where we can record the the podcast so
we should add this thank you note here
so what kind of technologies do you use
specifically which parts of the ws
something web service stack are you
using none I mean well WS you said not X
okay okay so okay so what are you using
this in this I I don't only III don't
only have one customer and okay so that
is a big customer here oh that big
customer that's interesting they started
with typical rendezvous yeah I was
basically a messaging middle world yes
fifty-five yes well that times the the
project was named an SOA project it was
an enterprise integration project and
it turned out later on that we could you
see the infrastructure aspects of
enterprise integration for SOA
infrastructure so yeah so it's also we
stayed with that technology but yeah we
as I said we have different countries
involved in that company and when we try
to connect two countries both using tip
one everyone turned out that they
couldn't talk to each other so this is
not no guarantee so so even if you
decide on your protocol on your
infrastructure protocol whether it's web
service or something else this that's
not enough to to be sure that you are
interoperable and and those who know the
web service standardization disaster
let's say that way is some you know that
that's what I wanted to get I see okay
yeah well we have we have about I think
well these days we have about between 60
and 80 different web service standards
and we use in the meantime we use web
services but it's only part of our
middleware we have mappings between web
services and other technologies the data
structures are defined as an XML schema
globally and then you transport them
using a TIBCO and web services that what
i yeah our our repositories are our
language that describes and the
semantics and the signature and the
interfaces are not proprietary for
specific infrastructure yeah
protocol well yes and well okay let me
first finish the other sentence that is
it's really interesting to see that we
have something like 60 between 60 and 80
standards and that you have additional
standards that provide interoperability
of these standards and like the vsi
basic profile which this is an
organization founded only to gain
interoperability using the web service
Stan
I mean that says something and in
practice they they they I think they
made something like like a hundred
twenty requirements additional
requirements or constraints and and 24 I
think extensions to web to the five
basic web service standards five of
sixty or seventy and now they say you
are interoperable which does not mean
that you are really into a parable you
still have to decide some things when
you realize us way but but it works
better you can connect your best talker
Microsoft BizTalk Webster with with an I
don't know an excess open-source
generated lava adapter so so what would
it be would be schema for data
description and then basically WSDL 1.1
to describe services if you have
services if you have web services and
what else is there in this WSI
interoperability thing well in the in
the it's called the the WSI basic
profile 1.1 which is round one and they
standardized um well the low level
technology with protocols which is XML
and HTTP so some certain things beside
that they started as ice the interface
language with this which is with calor
WSDL and which standardized the protocol
on top of HTTP which with soap and
beside that they they Sun alight that
the uddi the broker or the naming
service of web service but this doesn't
doesn't play such an important role in
basic web services communication
business process integration this is
from your point of view is this are you
doing like orchestration and process
modeling at your I always make must make
sure I don't mention the name of the
company since everybody kind of knows
what that company is but so do you use
this everybody knows yeah you know I
know it so we hear everybody know it you
know it I know it but so do you use
business process modeling and and the
stuff or are you just doing the service
layer well of course we do we have
business process modeling otherwise we
can't come from from new functionality
to running IT software the question is
whether we use the specific appropriate
technology supported way maybe web
services things should be used to
realize business process modeling for
example using people as a standard you
do this or you don't do this we do a
little bit of that okay I mean yeah we
we currently try to use people in as an
orchestration engine well for that we
had to use beta software of some vendors
I would say it's it's a pretty good
concept for common business processes
but the tooling is well let's say in the
second generation with this which is I
learned it from a Gregor hopper that
that it is the hockey stick function so
the hockey stick function generation of
tooling is up to a certain degree of
complexity it's pretty flat and then
there comes where the stick gets up to
the hand so if you raise a certain level
then a complexity or the effort for tool
yeah is raises more than the complexity
you have so I think we are in that state
and you need that say to get good tools
but you need some time to deal with this
these things okay although we wanted to
talk about non technical aspect somehow
we still talked about technical stuff
probably my questions here so let's look
at more organizational issues what do
you need to change in an organization in
order to make it as a way compatible how
do you how do organizations change too
be able to adopt an SLA successfully
okay I did that the most important point
of SOA is distributed computing yeah we
have that and distributed business
processing and distributed business
processing doesn't start with
implementation
it starts with yeah well design it
starts with high level design guess for
example you are a company and you need
some additional functionality or you
need some new you business model and you
want to realize this in your systems
then you have to break down this
functionality that would be less part of
your business process modeling process
and to some extent you say well this is
should be IT support and so you you
break down things however you have your
running systems you have your existing
backends that play a role and these let
me say backends are involved in this new
functionality now in the past we had
these monolithic fifteens that that
could you could give them the task in to
introduce this new functionality I
realize it in your IT system this
doesn't work any longer they you have
different departments different
providing different services because
they are responsible for different
things you have billing you have
customer relations you have fulfillment
and these are really different big
backends as ap systems
host j2ee server farms whatsoever and
now you want to introduce a new
functionality that means every back end
has to do something and it only makes
sense together distributed business
process so you start with an with an
high level design or what is usually
these days called a solution design up
above the different departments you have
the different departments you have in
your company like a bit like CRC cards
that you would like to associate
responsibilities and collaborations with
departments that might be one technique
things are connected
yeah but but the most important point is
there is something above the different
departments and I think you you are you
need a project culture you are getting
from a department wrapping to a
cross-cutting project currently you also
need the Department Carter these are the
back ends yeah but you need a project
culture and and it's in the hands of the
project cultures to drive the whole
thing to get the job right try to do
that with with all the existing
departments that usually about decide
everything on a new solution so this is
the hard part and and it also
contradicts to some extent to what you
said before because you said each
department or provider pack and should
be responsible for its own services and
so that's the one aspect or the one
viewpoint and now I said there is
another viewpoint which is more like
cross-cutting or orthogonal which looks
at introducing a new piece of
functionality into all these systems so
that altogether it makes sense yes and
and and for example in the mobile phone
company they they invented new arc
charts for that they said we have the
departments but we also have the
solution management departments would
where somehow high level above
everything and and they are project
departments so I mean they they get the
task here's a new function like they
wanna have make a high level design go
to the different departments asked for
their effort to realize this and then we
see the business case mm-hmm we we know
or we have an idea what brings us a new
business functionality and then we know
the price for realizing it and then we
decide and this is interesting in the
mobile phone company every three month
we have a meeting where we decide on a
new release what we realize and and
they're all these solutions
come together and we know the benefit we
know the the different efforts the
different Department has and now we have
to they have to find an ideal solution
to get the best benefit for the company
as a whole all departments should have
tasks for about a hundred percent of
their real effective time yeah and then
you follow that in realization and the
solution manager sees well because in
practice of course things change and you
find bugs so and and it's very important
that with this business model you
collaborate because if there's for
example one department is a profit
center and says okay I have I can give
you this service here I'd be have a
service that does it for you but it's
slightly different and it causes several
many costs for the other departments
yeah that then it's bad design and you
pay for that and in the long term so you
say the typical cost center designs
where you have these islands in your
companies who which make sure that they
make profit as much as possible
that doesn't work if you want to
introduce cross-cutting distributed
processes because then the people will
say I don't care what the others do III
do it so that I maximize my own profit
or you have a profit model in your
organization that deals with these facts
right so that you can that you can pay
but but then what I mean that means you
have to break down your new
functionality not only technically and
from a business point of view also from
a from a pricing point of view and I
don't think that works so so we have we
have the good fact that that our IT
departments have a have a flat budget so
though they they don't they are not
profit centers and and we say well but
this flat battle is we wanna we want to
get the best the most functional charity
the most functionality we have to cook
get the best in the business and yeah I
mean and that but it changes a lot and
if you don't have support from from CEOs
for this kind of different thinking in
companies then you will fail I've seen
that and it's interesting you can say
SOA is some kind of problem detector if
if the if a company is really able to
collaborate yeah and if not they might
blame SOA for it they say before we
introduce this way everything worked
fine I mean it didn't work fine David
that you have that in reality you have
distributed processes without
introducing SOA and Universal but it's
not explicit yeah now assume your
current job is finished with your mobile
phone company you take off two months
and rebreathe and then you go to your
next customer and your job is to
introduce an SLA there how do you do
this how do you start what are the steps
Oh first of all make sure that
management is behind you that there is
the understanding that SOA is a company
or business strategy and and technology
is only part of it no and I talked
already about the the problems of
Business Process Management but there
are many other processes you have to
introduce in your company for service
life cycles for solution management and
also for example more technically for
model driven development because you
generate a lot of code for
interoperability and and and so you need
processes in practice that work for
there and well first of all I don't see
no other change but introducing SOA in a
way that it evolves in a company start
small start small but think big but well
think big and think small start small
think big and think think small
I mean it okay
well start small is clear to evolve it
iterate to get to get the best and to
understand how business aspects process
aspects architectural aspect influence
each other um think big because well you
have large systems yeah and you for
example
must not introduce bottlenecks but also
think small in a way I think simple
maybe think simple yeah maybe that's
better in a way that you avoid the the
yakhni principle so you ain't gonna need
it principle which means you you think
you need some kind of flex leads
flexibility that that does not exactly a
tendency have also seen that that people
think they have to care for all kinds of
possibilities and then they build this
huge complex system with all kinds of
dynamic runtime facilities and you're
never needed yeah I give you a simple
example we have in in our systems we
have started with the idea that it is
easy that a service can move on from
Brownback and to another and of course
this to realize that you need some kind
of in in directing it turned out that in
practices is never happened
but it turned also out that this cost
cost a lot of problems in our code
generation processes etc so we have
difficulties to for example to debug
services because suddenly you have due
to the indirection you have a name
change you have a symbolic name and that
this is mapped to a real name
just enjoy India I look upset ok mmm for
example yeah so this is a typical
example where I learned yeah don't start
with these things or don't start with
the repository so first things first
so a but in but don't ya forget that the
result is a large system yeah but that's
in that typical that in order to build
large systems and to build scalable
systems you
should keep the that the individual
building the individual building blocks
and the rules that govern the
architecture as simple as possible yeah
yeah sure
yeah I mean I mean I mean simplicity is
a principle how often do you see that in
practice I mean I'm saying yeah of
course it's it's good to keep things
simple but I'm saying that especially if
you try to build big systems or general
things even what you that that is a
forest to drive things even if you look
at the HTTP simplicity right and it's
even more key the bigger you get yes yes
and for several reasons one reason is
well all these simplicity scales from
even from the understanding of the
people I mean you have hundreds of
programmers involved and they have to
understand their role what they do their
constraints and they won't understand it
if you have complicated architecture
nature's yeah so out of large systems
yeah I mean I think there is there's
different viewpoints I mean an
architecture can be complex and and
sophisticated internally if you have a
well-defined
what I'd like to call programming model
of well-defined view of the architecture
that developers see well I mean now I
come back to web services yeah there's
something that there are more than only
the the standardization problem wrong
with rep service yeah we know I mean I
know I mean another big problem is that
web service is a protocol
I am Senate not an API standard yeah
which leads to the fact that the
responsibility often for from from
enterprise integration teams or SOA
competence center ends and will still
fire and each team uses their own code
generator so so how to well is so two of
them they make it they they make it very
different which is definitely not simple
especially as they will deal with all
with the same problems and the
with them in different ways so what you
say is yeah our task is to write to
provide a very simple way for the date
for the business teams to work exactly
usually leads to the task of providing
them an API or tooling or tooling that
generates an IP I guess and for example
we will change infrastructure in that
mobile phone company right now and we
can keep the API we switched from
typical to web services and we keep the
API and that is for for the business
people nothing change and this is this
is key and and I see too much people
only focusing on Web Services and of
course a web service of the even if it's
a standard in ten years there will be a
difference than Atlas and and to be very
careful to to that you that you use web
services only if you if you sure now we
come to the infrastructure aspects of
our problem don't expose all that stuff
to application code to the business
logic Oracle and not to design etc so
for example if people have this strange
idea of specifying services using this
tool this is something very strange ask
I mean I have talked about that before
but I just like to hear this from you
for some reason what so is incomplete
they they don't deal with non functional
attributes and whistle is too broad so
usually you have to constraint things
you are that are allowed there it's also
true for XML schema I guess yeah yeah
that's part of it XML schema yes so you
for example think very carefully with
enumerations yeah think carefully with
choices inheritance inheritance because
sorry to say that I know a lot of Java
guys are here but Java is not the only
programming language here and if you
build large systems and you integrate
legacy which is large systems our legacy
period then you you you deal with
programming language
that have a problem with inheritance and
you can you can deal with that but it's
also so that's always something I say
design your data structures for example
with simply your mouth diagrams you only
have attributes objects you may be
distinguished between you know
composition relationship and on
composition you may be distinguished
between entities and value types and
then you have cardinalities on the
references and that's solid yeah and
then the other ways structural data
types yeah
Stratus record structs and arrays lists
some kind of these the end based on some
and let the most solid and way to be
sure that your investments yeah work for
the next yes so as we slowly about
certainly wrap up this session I guess
another term I've been hearing quite
often in the terms of in context of SOA
is is what people call governance sounds
a bit very much business to me so can
you explain what what governance stands
for what is that what role does it play
well what governance
first of all stands for itself I mean
governance is the governance of that
making sure that things turn out to be
right so SOA governance which is usually
part of IT governance in your company
has the idea of making ensuring that SOA
works is that it's performed right and
as you have learned now in the meantime
this includes not only infrastructure it
includes architectural aspects and
processes and it all comes together so
so when you introduce some team that
establish or adopts an SOA in your
company then yeah these team should be
able to govern the whole topic in a
useful way that all comes together and
works together and there's like a
steering committee oh boy steering are
usually is usually the name for the
people
steering over the governance team that
is I think governance is more often
called an integration competence center
so that you say there is some team
responsible that all makes things
together you can also say that it's a
System Architect of SOA but as I said
it's system I had ignored
only four technical aspects system the
system means the enterprise yeah not
technically yeah and one of the major
reason SOA fades and practice is a lack
of governance which is always combined
with a lack of understanding what SOA is
about because otherwise they would know
that that you need some kind of
government in its governance but I've
also very often seen that very often
sounds like I've seen hundreds of SOA
predict that that's not the case right
now that I've seen I've seen it several
times that one problem of of the team's
responsible for establishing SOA in the
company don't fulfill two very important
requirements this team should have
requirement number one you have to
establish decentralization to the
extreme that means make sure that you
are not involved any longer so establish
a central team decentralized processes
and it's difficult for some people to
work on a task that so that they give up
responsibility and control and the other
thing um is you want to establish
service orientation service has to do
with service and service this is a team
that is a service team for the business
teams in the company so you say the
business people rule and
of the IT people right they asked for
the they defined agreements they asked
for problems and I I've seen a lot of
problems because the central teams were
some kind of ivory towers and not having
time and not enough resources is also
management yeah yeah to go to the
business teams and to work to work with
and explaining the idea the concept
developing the first adapting adapters
and then learning what went wrong see
seeing how the process lags in practice
and then making making some changes so
homework homework is so important for
successful so ah yeah that the homework
is done that all you made it might have
all the concepts all the tools so you
may not just talk about it but actually
really do things yeah that these the
central teams have to be part of using
process of the processes very hard yes
and yeah let's say well understand
yourself as a service provider for your
company or companies okay anything else
you want to say before we wrap this up
sure I mean I have no idea when this
talk will be published but there is some
advertisement hey there is a book coming
out I'm currently writing one is going
to be published the book roughly how the
ideas mid of 2007 we can make sure that
that the podcast will be at the
mid-2000s sure that's that pre great
yeah so so as I in practice by O'Reilly
and this will contain hopefully a lot of
useful things I have talked about here
and a bit a little bit more ok cool so
thank you very much for being on the
show and you've Marcus
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se
- radio net although we prefer entries
in our comment system on the website so
other people can see what you think
Software Engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details
[Music]